# HUANG XIE Doctoral Researcher

6+ years in developing machine learning models for audio understanding, audio-language multimodal learning, and audio information retrieval, and 10+ years in software development. Proficiency in machine learning, audio/text processing, data analysis, web development, and Python & Java programming.



# **Personal Info**

- Huang Xie
- huang.xie@outlook.com
- +358 40 3219383
- Tampere, Finland
- github.com/xieh97
- in linkedin.com/in/huang-xie-28b7872bb
- orcid.org/0000-0001-7609-8049

# Languages

ChineseNativeEnglishProfessionalFinnishBeginner

# **Referees**

#### **Prof. Tuomas Virtanen**

- ② Tampere University
- tuomas.virtanen@tuni.fi

### Assoc. Prof. Okko Räsänen

- Tampere University
- okko.rasanen@tuni.fi

# **Employment**

#### Doctoral Researcher | Research Assistant

03/2019 - Present

- Audio Research Group, Tampere University, Finland
  - Developed large machine learning models (e.g., CNNs, RNNs, transformers) for audio understanding, audio-language multimodal learning, and audio information retrieval, using techniques like self-supervised learning, contrastive learning, and transfer learning.
  - Constructed, analyzed, and processed large-scale audio/text datasets, performing tasks like feature extraction, semantic analysis, classification, and context-based retrieval.
  - Published 9+ first-authored scientific papers in top-tier journals and conferences (e.g., IEEE/ACM TASLP, SPL, ICASSP).

### **Software Engineer**

10/2015 - 05/2018

- P Bohai Commodity Exchange, Tianjin, China
  - Developed key features for CloudBoce (%, an E-Commerce platform), including shopping cart, order processing, and product management.
  - Collaborated with cross-functional teams (e.g., UI designers, product managers) to define, design, and ship new features.
  - Troubleshot and debugged issues related to performance, crashes, and other bugs, ensuring smooth and stable user experience.

#### **Principal Java Developer**

07/2014 - 09/2015

- Qingdao Industrial Software Research Institute, Qingdao, China
  - Led the development and delivery of multiple enterprise-grade software solutions (e.g., BPM, CMS), overseeing the full project lifecycle from planning to deployment.
  - Mentored junior developers and performed code reviews to maintain high coding standards and best practices.
  - Collaborated with cross-functional teams to define requirements, troubleshoot issues, and deliver high-quality software on schedule.
  - Presented technical solutions to non-technical stakeholders, and managed technical documentation and reports.

# **Skills**

**Programming**: Python, Java, JavaScript, SQL, C/C++, Kotlin **Machine Learning**: PyTorch, Tensorflow, scikit-learn, Ray, Spark

Data Analysis: NumPy, SciPy, Pandas, NLTK, Matplotlib

Web Development: Java EE, Spring, Hibernate, Django, Flask, MySQL, Git

### **Education**

PhD in Signal Processing and Machine Learning	01/2021 - Present
<b>♀</b> Tampere University, Tampere, Finland	
M.Sc. in Data Engineering and Machine Learning	08/2018 - 11/2020
<b>♀</b> Tampere University, Tampere, Finland	
M.Eng. in Software Engineering	09/2010 - 06/2014

**Q** University of Science and Technology of China, Hefei, China

# **Activities**

- ₱ Reviewer for IEEE/ACM TASLP, SPL, ICASSP, WASPAA, DCASE, etc.
- Task coordinator for Language-based Audio Retrieval and Automated Audio Captioning in DCASE Challenge 2022 (%), 2023 (%), and 2024 (%).

